<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian on Bayesian Statistics and Functional Programming </title>
    <link>/categories/bayesian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian on Bayesian Statistics and Functional Programming </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/bayesian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian Monte Carlo in R</title>
      <link>/2019/07/31/hamiltonian_monte_carlo_in_r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/31/hamiltonian_monte_carlo_in_r/</guid>
      <description>Hamiltonian Monte Carlo Metropolis-Hastings requires the specification of a proposal distribution, the log-likelihood and prior distributions for the parameters. The proposal distribution is often a multivariate Normal distribution with mean corresponding to the previous value of the parameters, the covariance of the proposal distribution is a tuning parameter. This proposal results in random walk behaviour and although the MH algorithm is guaranteed to converge it can take a long time to get satisfactory draws from the posterior distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Markov Chain Monte Carlo in R with Rcpp</title>
      <link>/2019/02/11/efficient_mcmc_using_rcpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/11/efficient_mcmc_using_rcpp/</guid>
      <description>Bivariate Normal Model This post considers how to implement a simple Metropolis scheme to determine the parameter posterior distribution of a bivariate Normal distribution. The implementation is generic, using higher-order-functions and hence can be re-used with new algorithms by specifying the un-normalised log-posterior density and a proposal distribution for the parameters. The built-in parallel package is used fit multiple chains in parallel, finally the Metropolis algorithm is reimplemented in C++ using Rcpp which seemlessly integrates with R.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>