<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Running on Bayesian Statistics and Functional Programming </title>
    <link>/categories/running/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Running on Bayesian Statistics and Functional Programming </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/running/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sampling from a distribution with a known CDF</title>
      <link>/2019/02/25/inverse-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/25/inverse-sampling/</guid>
      <description>A distribution with an inverse cumulative distribution function (CDF) can be sampled from using just samples from \(U[0, 1]\). The inverse CDF (sometimes called the quantile function) is the value of \(x\) such that \(F_X(x) = Pr(X \leq x) = p\). Consider a that a transformation \(g: [0, 1] \rightarrow \mathbb{R}\), exists which takes a value sampled from the standard uniform distribution \(u \sim U[0, 1]\) and returns a value distributed according to the target distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Statistical Model for Finishing Positions at the National Cross Country</title>
      <link>/2019/02/22/national-cross-country/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/02/22/national-cross-country/</guid>
      <description>Area Results Download the results from Power of ten for northern, midlands, southern and national.
 A linear model The goal is to fit a model, where the outcome is the position at the national and the input is the position at the northern XC. This then allows us to determine the quality of the field at each XC and determine what position you are likely to finish in the National this season given a result in the area championships.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harrier League Cross Country</title>
      <link>/2017/10/26/harrier-league-cross-country/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/26/harrier-league-cross-country/</guid>
      <description>The Harrier League is a cross country running league with seven fixtures across the North East of England in the 2017/18 season across the winter months from September ’17 until March ‘18.
The Harrier League is unique to other cross country fixtures because the senior runners are divided up into slow, medium and fast packs. In the senior men’s race, the slow runners start first followed 2 minutes 30 seconds later by the medium pack runners, then a further 2 minutes 30 seconds by the fast pack runners.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>